A Guide to the Reginald M. Archibald papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA146
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Laboratory notes
  - Laboratory notes and records
    - Laboratory procedures and preparations, pp 0-65 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Plasma proteins, Colorimetric method for the micro determination of arginase, Colorimetric micro Kjeldahl technique, Micro Kjeldahl by Nesslerization.
    - Barbiturates, 1944 November-1945 March; pp 1-74 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Transfusion reactions - RRC fractionation, 1942 April-June; pp 0-47 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Nephritic Urine Studies, 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Includes: Thomas M. Rivers "Memorandum to Heads of Services and Physicians Taking Care of Patients" and treatment and diagnosis of diseases.
    - Nephritic series, 1942 February-1943 January (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Includes:
      - "Creatine and Creatine in Blood or Urine", 1 p typescript
      - Phillips, Hamilton, Archibald, Stanley, Becker and Franpton, "A-V and Urine Values from Glycocyamine and Arginine in Dog after Peanuts", 1 p typescript. pp 0-135
    - Liver extract urea... and Ascorbic acid, 1944 August-1945 January; pp 1-110 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Includes literature notes.
    - Determination of urea by Citrulline and Allantoin, 1943 December-1944 June; pp 0-184 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Includes Dr. Archibald's comments on mss submitted for publication in JBC: Hunter, A. and Downs, C.E., "The Measurement of Arginase Activity", Christman, A.A., Foster, P.W. and Esterer, M.B., "The allantoin content of blood".
    - Citrulline II, 1944 May-August; pp 0-38 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Decarboxylase, 1945 November-1946 March; 5" Hollinger (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Decarboxylase, 1946 April-July (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Decarboxylase, 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Includes blood lysine results and cultural requirements.
    - Tsoandrosterone, Dehydroisoandrosterone, 1947 October-1948 March; pp 1-108 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Includes methyl testosterone and estrone..
    - Lab notes [re] Effect of acetate ion on the reaction of sodium monofluoroacetate on rats, 1947 November 7-1948 January 21; pp 0-7 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Chromatographic absorption curves, 1947 December-1948 May; pp 1-39 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Crocker, Charity notes, 1947-1949 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Colorimetric absorption of urea, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Benzine elution of ago dyes, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Method used to determine cholesterol, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Uric acid determination, 1948-1952; pp 1-32 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Enzyme data, 1950-January 1951 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Rhodanese activity (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Experimental data on alkaline phosphatase and various procedures by others including Stanford Moore and William Stein, "Photometric Ninhydrin Method for Use in the Chromatography of Amino Acids" JBC 176 (1948 373-376), 1948-1955; pp 0-149 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Development of urea method, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - RELN of Metacarpals, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Manuscripts, 5" Hollinger
  - Archibald, R.M. Frontiers of Biochemistry. Chemical and Engineering News 30 (1952) 4473-4476 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Includes several drafts of ms and figures (photographs) and correspondence regarding revisions.
    This paper is a record of opening address to the Biochemical Section of the 1st International Congress of Clinical Pathology.
  - Sauvé, G. Determination of Proline in the Plasma. Federation Proceedings 13 (1954), circa 1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    [Publication information Draft with R.M. Archibald corrections. from Box (14) 6].
  - Archibald, R.M. Gasometric Procedures for Amino Acids. In: Methods in Enzymology, Vol III. (Colowick, S.P. and Kaplan, N.O., Editors), Academic Press, New York, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes mss and correspondence with S.P. Colowick and others.
    I. Determination of Aliphatic Amino Nitrogen by Nitrous Acid, pp 458-462.
    II. Gasometric Ninhydrin Determination of Free Amino Acids, pp 1041-1044.
    III. Manometric Arginase Determination of of Arginine. pp 1044-1047.
    IV. Determination of Amino Acids by Specific Bacterial Decarboxylases, pp 1047-1049.
  - Archibald, R.M. Colorimetric Measurement of Uric Acid. Clinical Chemistry 3 (1957) 102-105 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes drafts of ms as well as correspondence with Carl Alper re publishing Archibald method paper simultaneously with Alper paper. Also includes several letters asking for help in using method.
  - Archibald, R.M. Nitrogen by the Kjeldahl Method. In: American Association for Clinical Chemists, Standard Methods of Clinical Chemistry, v. 2, New York, Academic Press, 1958. pp 91-99, Includes drafts and galley proof of ms. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes 1956 correspondence with David Seligson, reprints by others on Kjeldahl method... including Heller, Plazin and D.D. Van Slyke, "A Study of Conditions for Kjeldahl Determination of Nitrogen in Proteins" JBC 176 (1948) 1401-1420. (Method in this ms based on Heller, Plazin and Van Slyke paper.)
  - Archibald, R.M. Book review: Sobotka, H. and Stewart, CP., Editors, Advances in Clinical Chemistry. Vol. 1. Academic Press, New York, New York, Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    [no other publication information in file].
    Includes correspondence, original and revised drafts of review and galley proof.
  - Archibald, R.M., Finby, M. and DeVito, F. Endocrine Significance of Short Metacarpals. Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism 19 (1959) 1312-1322, 2 folders
    - untitled (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Editorial correspondence, drafts of ms, referees comments, photographs of figures. Paper also accepted and presented by Dr. Archibald at Endocrine Society meeting.
    - untitled (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Working material and drafts and photographs of figures
      [Same as folder 7].
  - The Aarskog-Scott Syndrome, 1972 1975 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Includes abstract and paper of case presentation by R.M. Archibald, "The Aarskog-Scott Syndrome" at 1972 June 12-16, Baltimore, Md., Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions/National Foundation-March of Dimes, 5th Conference on the Clinical Delineation of Birth Defects. Also includes a printed announcement of conference, preliminary and partial list of participants and topics. An RU Hospital outpatient case history in 1972, correspondence with V.A. McKusick, James German and others, correspondence with parents and drafts of case report by Archibald and German and drafts of ms by Archibald and German published in 1975, working material and rough draft of ms by others [re] Aarskog-Scott Syndrome.
    - Archibald, R.M. The Aarskog-Scott Syndrome. Case presentation by Dr. Archibald, 1972
    - Archibald, R.M. and German, J. The Aarskog-Scott Syndrome in Four Brothers, 1975
      In: Malformation Syndromes, Birth Defects: Original Article Series Vol II, no 2, pp 25-29
- Abstracts, methods, bibliographies and course in biochemistry and correspondence, 1945-1949 1957-1961; 2½" Hollinger.
  - Abstract articles on hormones and special methods of preparation of hormones, 1945-1947 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Biochemistry Lectures and Bibliography in Biochemistry, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Includes various bibliographies in biochemistry and biochemistry lectures outlines and texts of some lectures, duplicated material for Diagnostic Methods and History Taking and some notes.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Primarily correspondence requesting some hormones and steriods.
    Also includes duplicated materials: "The Steroid Hormone Structure and Its Variations", "Endocrine Disorders of Childhood and Adolescence".
    - Notes and price list of various hormones submitted to Dr. Archibald by Edmund J. Bent
  - Assorted correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Angeluscheff, Z.D., 1959
    - Beam, A.G., 1960
    - Behrendt, H. [re] colorimetric urea method, 1960
    - Beveridge, J.M.R., 1958
    - Bongiovanni, A.M. [re] honoring Waldo Nelson. Includes Dr. Archibald's statement about Nelson, 1960
    - McNamara, A., 1957
    - Flinn, W.R. [re] opening window at night in Archibald lab to dissipate organic solvents, 1958
    - Frampton, E.W., 1958
      Includes curriculum vitae and photograph, of Frampton, E.W.
    - Gillmore, G.B. Mrs., 1960
    - Gould, R.F., 1959-1960
      Indications are R.M. Archibald reviews Bernard S. Strauss, "An Outline of Chemical Genetics" for Chemical and Engineering News ca 1960. [Not listed in Archibald bibliography]
    - Keville, W.A.[re] Archibald, Finby and DeVito abstract of "Endocrine Significance of Short Metacarpals" for 1960-1961 Year Book of Radiology
    - Lawson, L.W., 1961
    - McCreary, J.F., 1959
    - Maddock, J.K. [re] proposed volume edited by Litwack, G. and Kritchewsky, D., "Hormonal Regulation of Enzyme Action", 1961
      Encls. Copies of: Prospectus, list of possible contributors and Editors covering letter.
    - Malm, O.J., 1960
    - Martinek, R.G. [re] pancreatic lipase, 1960
    - Moritz, H.C., 1961
    - Mujahed, Z. [re] Archibald presentation 1960 March 30, New York Hospital/CMC, 1959-1960
    - Nappi, P.E., 1959
    - Phillips, R.A., 1959-1961
      In 1959 [re] T.F. Dixon, and in 1960 [re] T.C. Tung
    - Pollock, J.J., 1958
      [See Also under: Smith, S.B.]
    - Reiss, F., 1960
    - Rich, C., 1960
    - Smith, Stanley B., 1958
      [See also under: Pollock, J.J.]
    - Wolin, Louis, 1960
- Electrophoresis of patients' serum 1-75, 1966-1970; 5" Hollinger
  - 1-16, 1968 March-September (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 17-31 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 32-40 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 41-48 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 49-62 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 63-75 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Reprints by R.M. Archibald, 1930-1976; 2½ Hollinger
  Includes reprints by others 1954, 1977.
  - 1930 1932 1935 1936 1939 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1942-1949 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1950-1955 1957-1959 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 1963 1965 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1971 1975 1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Reprints by others
    - reprint by Gaston Sauvé in Federation Proceedings (introduced by R.M. Archibald), 1954 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - reprint by J.P. Whalen, M. Horwith, L. Krook, I. MacIntyre, E. Mena, F. Viteri, B. Torun and E.A. Nunez in Am J Roentgenol, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous materials, 1985 November 25; 2½" Hollinger
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Received from R.M. Archibald, 25 November 1985.
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    American Journal of Medicine. Ms review by R.M. Archibald.
    - Bialostozky, E [re] delayed growth, 1977
    - Hsu, H.. Includes Hsu curriculum vitae and bibliography, 1977
    - Moss, L.E., 1977
    - Penndorf, P.R., 1976
    - Seitz, F. [re] Jacques Genest, 1977
    - Terris, C.A. [re] Delayed growth, 1977
  - Archibald, R.M. Chemical Characteristics and Physiological Roles of Glutamine. Chemical Reviews 37 (1945) 161-208, Manuscript (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Editorial and other corres and 2 pp typescript with same title as published ms.
  - R.M. Archibald. Unidentified, circa 1973 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Pages 11 and 12 (photocopies) of primarily bibliography possibly for grant application.
  - RU Duplicated Material, 1972 1977 1982 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - M. McCarty/R.M. Archibald (as member of RU Hospital Committee), 1972 September 27
    - Preliminary schedule includes January 1973 presentation by R.M. Archibald for annual re-review of programs involving human subjects, 1973 January
  - Organizations, Duplicated/printed materials (Box 15, Folder 5)
    R.M. Archibald involved in.
    Includes: Lawson Wilkins Pediatric Endocrine Society. 1984 R.M. Archibald a current member of.
    Includes duplicated material of: Minutes of meeting, May 1, 1984, List of new members, Financial report, Committee membership list, Current update on June 1985 meeting, Current membership list.
    - Madison Square Boys' Club, Annual Report, 1976; Printed pamphlet
      R.M. Archibald listed as member of Board of Directors.
    - National Academy of Clinical Biochemistry, circa 1977
      R.M. Archibald addressed as Fellow in 2 pp duplicated communication from Secretary.
- Miscellaneous Duplicated and Printed Material
  See: R.M. Archibald/Carolyn Kopp, 6 March 1986 in folder 1
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences and APS, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Federation of American Scientists, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - FASEB Newsletters, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - PHS-NIH various items, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Federal Grants and Contracts Weekly (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Thank you letters from students at Mark Twain Junior High School in Brooklyn to R.M. Archibald for his May 14, 1984 "Career Day" address on his work at RU, 1984 May 14; 2½" Hollinger (Box 16, Folder 1)
- R.M. Archibald, "Treatise on Analytical Chemistry. Section B, No. 56, Organic Analysis. Biological and Biochemical" The Rockefeller Institute, New York 21, New York, circa 1963; Carbon typescript, 175 pp., in 4 folders (Box 16, Folder 2-5)
- Mss. Draft, "Organic Analysis: Biological and Biochemical", undated; 176 pp (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
- Dental Training Grant File, 1965-1968 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Radioisotopes, 1969-1974 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Departmental Memos, 1951-1961 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1973-1974 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Personnel, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Safety Measures-Departmental, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Summer Employment, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Instructions to the Secretary, 1954-1957, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Laboratory Notebook: Absorption Curves, 1947-1948 (Box 17, Folder 11)